終局[しゅうきょく]:end/close/conclusion, 始める[はじめる]:to start|to open (e.g. a store)|to start ...
終局を始める前に
Before the finale begins, before we reach the end,
終極[しゅうきょく]:ultimate/final, 至る[いたる]:to arrive at (e.g. a decision)|to lead to (a place)|to come
終極に至る前に
I'm sure you, my dear readers, have not forgotten
開示[かいじ]:release (e.g. information)/disclosure (legal)/show, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
開示しなければならない物語が
残す[のこす]:to leave (behind, over)/to bequeath/to save
もうひとつだけ残されていることを
that there is a story left that I must disclose to you.
読者[どくしゃ]:reader, 諸兄[しょけい]:dear friends/(all of) you or those men, まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, てはい:arrangement/preparations|search (by police), てはい:tiles in a player's hand
読者諸兄(しょけい)もまさか忘れてはいないだろう
白状[はくじょう]:confession, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
白状すれば 僕としては忘れていて欲しかったところだし
Frankly, I would have wanted you to forget,
and even more so, would have wanted to forget it myself.
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 忘れる[わすれる]:to forget/to leave carelessly/to be forgetful of
それ以上に忘れていたかったところなのだが
Keeping it undisclosed,
secretly and sorrowfully
pretending it had never happened,
I would've liked to end this story about me.
問屋[とんや, といや]:wholesale store, 卸す[おろす]:to sell wholesale|to grate (e.g. vegetables)|to cut up fish, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
そうは問屋(とんや)が卸(おろ)しませんよ 阿良々木先輩
You won't get away so easily, Araragi.
Trying to hide something from me is foolish.
隠し事[かくしごと, かくしこと]:secret, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 無謀[むぼう]:reckless/thoughtless/rash, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
私の前で隠し事をしようだなんて
そんな無謀はおよしください
嘘[うそ, ウソ]:lie|mistake|unwise move|, 誤魔化し[ごまかし]:hanky-panky/juggling/cheating, 天敵[てんてき]:natural enemy
私は嘘や誤魔化しの天敵です
I am the nemesis of lies and deception.
先延ばし[さきのばし]:delay/putting off/procrastination, 後回し[あとまわし]:putting off/postponing, 捕食者[ほしょくしゃ]:predator
先延ばしや後回しの捕食者です
I am the predator of delay and postponement.
卓越[たくえつ]:preeminence/excellence/superiority, 詐欺師[さぎし]:swindler/imposter/crook, 泥舟[どろぶね]:boat to transport mud|(fictional) boat made of (dried) mud, 顛末[てんまつ]:circumstance/facts/details
卓越した詐欺師 貝木(かいき)泥舟(でいしゅう)の顛末を
あなただって知らないわけじゃあないでしょう?
You should be aware of what befell Kaiki Deishuu, the great fraud.
If you don't wish to end up like him, please tell your story.
語る[かたる]:to talk about|to recite|to indicate, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ああなりたくないのであれば 語ってくださいよ
Tell the story you've been so adamant to keep hidden until now.
頑な[かたくな]:obstinate/stubborn/mulish, ひた隠し[ひたかくし]:cover-up/hiding at all costs, してき:historic/historical, してき:pointing out/identification, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
あなたが頑(かたく)なに これまでひた隠しにしてきた
あのときの話を
I could tell from looking at her that she already knew exactly of the events being referred to,
様子[ようす]:state|appearance|sign, 限り[かぎり]:limit|degree|as far as possible||, 限り[きり]:end|bounds|delivery date (of a futures contract)||, 出来事[できごと, できこと]:incident/affair/happening, 既に[すでに, すんでに]:already/too late, 尽くす[つくす]:to exhaust|to devote|to do to exhaustion, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely
その様子を見る限りにおいて 彼女は
あのときの出来事について既に知り尽くしているようにも思えたが
問う[とう]:to ask|to charge (e.g. with a crime)|without regard to|, たとする:to appreciate/to be thankful, 空とぼける[そらとぼける]:to feign ignorance/to play dumb
そう問うたとしても 空とぼけるだけだろう
but had I confronted her with such a suspicion, she simply would have feigned ignorance.
私は何も知りませんよ
I know nothing.
You're the one who knows.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
あなたが知っているんです 阿良々木先輩
通り[とおり]:avenue|coming and going|flow (of water, air, etc.)||, 通り[どおり]:in accordance with|roughly|Street
その通り
She is right.
I know.
僕は知っている
とても:very/awfully|(not) at all
とてもよく知っている
I know very well what happened.
隠す[かくす]:to hide/to conceal
知っているからこそ 隠したかったのだが
And precisely because I know, I wished to hide it.
Reference
語る[かたる]:to talk about|to recite|to indicate
知っているからには 語らねばならない
And likewise because I know, I have to tell it.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
長い話になるぜ と僕は言う
This story will take a while, I said.
構う[かまう]:to mind|to care for|to prepare for||
構いませんとも
I don't mind.
野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 扇[おうぎ, おおぎ]:folding fan, 転校[てんこう]:changing schools, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, ヵ月[かげつ]:months (period of), 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, ハプニング:happening/unexpected incident
あれは 忍野扇が転校してくる
二ヵ月以上前のハプニングである
This story describes les événements of more than two months prior to Ougi transferring into our school.
夏休み[なつやすみ]:summer vacation/summer holiday, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 学期[がっき]:school term/semester, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from), 直後[ちょくご]:immediately following
夏休みが終わり 二学期が始まった直後
Summer break was over,
and the second term had just begun.
Emergency Button
His link to the vampire had been severed,
Naoetsu Private High School
吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker, ペアリング:pairing, 切る[きる]:to cut|to sever (connections, ties)|to turn off (e.g. the light)||, およそ:about/roughly|generally, 半年[はんとし, はんねん]:half year, 振り[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 振り[ぶり]:style/manner|after (period of time) again (e.g. meeting again after a year)
吸血鬼とのペアリングが切られ およそ半年振りに
and for the first time in about half a year,
Araragi Koyomi experienced being more or less human again.
生身[なまみ, しょうじん]:living flesh/flesh and blood|physical body of Buddha or a bodhisattva, 体感[たいかん]:bodily sensation/sense/experience, 暦[こよみ, れき]:calendar/almanac
ほぼ生身の "人間" を体感している阿良々木暦が
He didn't go to school.
学校[がっこう]:school
学校にも行かず
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
家にも帰らず
He didn't go home.
かつて:once/before|never yet, 専門家[せんもんか]:specialist/expert/professional, 野[の, や]:plain|hidden (structural) member|wild|, 寝床[ねどこ]:bed/berth/crib, 学習塾[がくしゅうじゅく]:private night-school/tutoring school (math, English, etc.), 跡[あと]:trace|site|scar, 跡[せき]:trace, 教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school
かつて専門家 忍野メメが寝床とした
学習塾跡の廃ビルのいち教室で
He was hiding in one of the classrooms in the decrepit
cram school that the specialist Oshino Meme had used
もてあます:to be too much for one/to find unmanageable/to be beyond one's control, 身を潜める[みをひそめる]:to hide oneself, 場面[ばめん]:scene/setting (e.g. of novel)
時間をもてあますように
身を潜(ひそ)めている場面から
to sleep in as though he had all the time in the world.
Tonight, 9:00 O'clock
Alone, Second Floor
Come To The Classroom
There's something
I want to ask you
Here the story begins,
物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend, 始まる[はじまる]:to begin|to happen (again)|to date (from)
物語は始まる
物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
物語は終わる
and here the story ends
人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
そして "彼" の人生も
together with the life of another.
続く[つづく]:to continue|to continue (without a break)|to occur again and again||, 続ける[つづける]:to continue/to keep up/to keep on, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death), ようやく:finally/at last|barely, ようやく:summary/digest, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
続き続けた "彼" の人生も
ようやく終わる
The life of one that time had tested in vain.
End Story
Shinobu Mail
Shinobu Mail Part One
End Story
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
阿良々木先輩
Araragi!
おっひざー!
Long time no see!
Long time no knee!
あげる:to raise/to elevate|to do up (one's hair), もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, スタイリッシュ:stylish, 悲鳴をあげる[ひめいをあげる]:to scream|to whine/to grumble
あげるにしても
もっとスタイリッシュな悲鳴をあげたいものだった
Having already screamed,
I only wished it had been more chic.
轢く[ひく]:to run over (with a vehicle)/to knock down, 蛙[かえる, かわず]:frog|kajika frog (Buergeria buergeri), みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 悲鳴[ひめい]:shriek/scream, あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 格好がつく[かっこうがつく]:to take shape/to look good enough to be shown publicly
車に轢(ひ)かれた蛙(かえる) みたいな悲鳴では
あまりに格好がつかない
Screaming like a frog run over
by a car is not particularly cool.
後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student, 出会い[であい]:meeting/rendezvous|confluence, がしら:top of ../head of ..|the moment that .., 膝蹴り[ひざげり]:knee strike/kneeing, 食らう[くらう]:to eat/to drink|to receive (e.g. a blow), 時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion, 格好[かっこう, かっこ]:shape|appearance|state||, 良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, まるっきり:completely/perfectly/totally, 望む[のぞむ]:to desire|to wish for|to see
まあ 後輩に 出会いがしらに膝蹴りを食らった時点で
格好良さなんてまるっきり望むべくもないんだが
Well, perhaps it's out of line to hope for a cool way of getting kneed in the face.
おっと:husband, おっと:uh-oh/oops/sorry, さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 一流[いちりゅう]:first-class|characteristic|school (e.g. of a performance art)|, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
おっと さすがは一流の阿良々木先輩
Nice one, Araragi.
早速[さっそく]:at once/immediately/without delay, 出会い[であい]:meeting/rendezvous|confluence, がしら:top of ../head of ..|the moment that .., 膝頭[ひざがしら]:kneecap, かける:to hang (e.g. picture)/to hoist (e.g. sail)|to sit, かける:to run (race, esp. horse)/to dash|to gallop (one's horse)
早速 出会いがしらと膝頭(ひざがしら)をかけてくるとは
Immediately making a pun on getting kneed in times of need is impressive.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 取る[とる]:to take|to steal|to eat||
これは一本取られたな
This round goes to you.
もっとも:most/extremely, もっとも:but then/although|reasonable, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
もっとも阿良々木先輩
However, Araragi.
恐縮[きょうしゅく]:feeling obliged/being grateful|shrinking back in fear, ながら:while/during|while, いただける:to be able to receive/to be able to take|to be able to eat, 膝頭[ひざがしら]:kneecap, 膝[ひざ, ヒザ]:knee|lap/knee and thigh (while sitting), 小僧[こぞう]:youngster|young Buddhist priest|young shopboy, 好き[すき]:liking/fondness/love, 好き[ずき]:-phil/-phile|being attractive (to)
恐縮ながら言わせていただけるのであれば 私は膝頭という言いかたよりも
膝小僧(こぞう)という言いかたのほうが好きだ
Permit me to say this, but I prefer the word patella over the word kneecap.
美少年[びしょうねん]:handsome youth (male)/pretty boy, 二人[ふたり, ににん]:two persons/two people/pair, 膝[ひざ, ヒザ]:knee|lap/knee and thigh (while sitting), 住まう[すまう]:to live/to reside/to inhabit, ほんの:mere/only/just, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck
美少年を二人 自分の膝に住まわせていると思うと
私はほんの少しだけ 幸せになれる
It's just one letter away from paella, and thinking something hot and Spanish is inside me makes me happy.
幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, 風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold
幸せって言葉をそんな風に使うな
You insult the word happiness.
美少年[びしょうねん]:handsome youth (male)/pretty boy, 限定[げんてい]:limit/restriction
あとなんで美少年限定なんだよ
Why must you make it so dirty?
美少年[びしょうねん]:handsome youth (male)/pretty boy, イメージ:(one's) image, 的[てき]:-like/typical, 的[まと]:mark/target, 稚児[ちご]:(festivity) page|baby|boys kept by pederasts, 稚児[やや, ややこ]:baby/child
美少年というか イメージ的にはお稚児(ちご)さんなのだ
Better yet would be knee chaps instead of kneecaps.
膝[ひざ, ヒザ]:knee|lap/knee and thigh (while sitting), 稚児[ちご]:(festivity) page|baby|boys kept by pederasts, 稚児[やや, ややこ]:baby/child, 住まう[すまう]:to live/to reside/to inhabit, 世の中[よのなか]:society/the world/the times, 少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 豊か[ゆたか]:abundant/wealthy|very, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
誰しも膝にお稚児さんを住まわせていると思うと
世の中が少しだけ 豊かに見えないか?
Doesn't the world seem richer if you think everyone has two little boys inside them?
豊か[ゆたか]:abundant/wealthy|very, 言葉[ことば, けとば]:language|word|speech, 風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold
豊かって言葉もそんな風に使うな
You insult the word rich!
膝[ひざ, ヒザ]:knee|lap/knee and thigh (while sitting), 稚児[ちご]:(festivity) page|baby|boys kept by pederasts, 稚児[やや, ややこ]:baby/child
僕の膝にはお稚児さんはいねえよ
I don't have little boys inside me!
つーか
Anyway.
一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 突っ込み[つっこみ, ツッコミ]:penetration|(in comedy) straight man|sex, どころ:particle used to indicate that what precedes it is an extreme example and strongly negates it, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 蹴る[ける]:to kick|to refuse/to reject, 一言[ひとこと, いちげん]:single word/a few words/brief comment, 謝る[あやまる]:to apologize/to apologise
一番の突っ込みどころは お前が先輩である僕を蹴ったことを
まだ一言も謝っていないということだ
My main criticism should probably be that you haven't apologized for kicking your senior.
謝る[あやまる]:to apologize/to apologise
謝る?
Apologize?
何を言っておるのだ
Don't be silly.
忠実[ちゅうじつ]:faithfulness/devotion/loyalty, 忠実[まめ]:sincerity|healthiness|faithfulness, 後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student, 河[かわ, がわ]:river/stream|the .... river, 河[ホー, かわ]:discarded tiles/discards, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 肉体[にくたい]:the body/the flesh, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document)
私こと忠実なる後輩 神原駿河は
いまや阿良々木先輩の肉体の一部のようなものではないか
Is my loyalty not such that I should be considered a part of your body?
Who would apologize to themselves for resting their cheek on their own knee?
膝[ひざ, ヒザ]:knee|lap/knee and thigh (while sitting), ほっぺた:cheek, 当たる[あたる]:to be hit|to touch|to be equivalent to||, 謝る[あやまる]:to apologize/to apologise
自分の膝がほっぺたに当たったからといって
人は自分に謝ったりしないだろう
That only sounds smart until you actually think about it!
立て[たて]:central|just (done)|counter for consecutive losses, 立て[だて]:particularly|indicates the number of horses or oxen drawing a carriage|indicates the number of movies, plays, etc. comprising a single program, 酷い[むごい]:cruel/merciless|tragic, 酷い[ひどい]:cruel|violent|very bad|, 理屈[りくつ]:theory/reason
立て板に水の酷い理屈だな!
To be honest, I know that you regenerate very quickly,
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 回復[かいふく]:restoration/rehabilitation|recovery (from an illness), 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive
まあ正直 阿良々木先輩は回復力が高いから
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, ニアミス:near-miss, 謝る[あやまる]:to apologize/to apologise
あれくらいのニアミスは別に謝らなくてもいいかなと思っているのはある
so I felt that a near-miss like that was no big deal.
正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
正直に言えばなんでも許されると思うなよ!
Honesty doesn't excuse everything!
歯[は]:tooth, 歯[よわい]:(one's) age, 砕ける[くだける]:to break (into pieces)|to collapse|to become less formal||
ちょっと歯ァ砕(くだ)けてんじゃねえか
Look, you knocked out a tooth...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
どうした阿良々木先輩
What's wrong, Araragi?
急[きゅう]:urgent|sharp|rapid||, 風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold, プロポーション:proportion/proportionate width, じろじろ:staringly/scrutinizing/scrutinising
急にそんな風に
私のプロポーションをじろじろ見たりして
You seem interested in my proportions.
プロポーション:proportion/proportionate width
プロポーションを見てるんじゃない
I wasn't checking out your proportions.
What?
プロポーション:proportion/proportionate width
プロポーションを見ずに私の何を見るのだ?
If you weren't checking them out, why else would you look at me?
プロポーション:proportion/proportionate width, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
私にはプロポーションくらいしか見るべきところはないだろう
Is that not the best thing about me?
謎[なぞ]:riddle/puzzle|enigmatic, 卑屈[ひくつ]:menial/meanness/servility, 発揮[はっき]:exhibition/demonstration/show, 高校[こうこう]:senior high school/high school, スター:star (cinema, sports, etc.)/celebrity/idol
謎の卑屈(ひくつ)さを発揮するな
直江津高校のスター
Stop with the sudden humility!
You're Naoetsu High School's best athlete.
じろじろ:staringly/scrutinizing/scrutinising, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care, 無用[むよう]:useless|unnecessary|not on business|, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
そんなじろじろ見なくとも
心配は無用だ 阿良々木先輩
You don't have to look at me with such concern, Araragi.
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
心配?
Concern?
心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
僕がお前の何を心配してるって言うんだよ
Is there something I should be concerned about?
Don't play dumb.
またまた:again (and again)/once again|You're kidding!, とぼける:to play dumb/to feign ignorance|to play the fool
またまたとぼけちゃって
You're such a gentleman, Araragi.
気遣い[きづかい]:consideration/concern/fear, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
気遣いの人だものな 阿良々木先輩は
But don't worry. You can trust your junior some more.
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student, 信用[しんよう]:confidence/dependence/credit
だがあなたはもう少し あなたの後輩を信用してよい
大丈夫
No worries.
I left the bra home.
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 外す[はずす]:to unfasten|to remove|to leave|
ちゃんとブラは外してきた
Bra
Now I'm starting to be concerned!
本気[ほんき]:seriousness/earnestness/truth, 心配[しんぱい]:worry/concern|care
僕はお前が本気で心配だよ!
Bra
No Bra
Perverted
Girl
My hoodie is rather thick,
so you probably can't tell by looking at me,
如何[どう, いかが]:how/in what way/how about, 如何[いかん]:how/in what way|circumstances, ジャージ:jersey, 生地[きじ]:cloth|one's true character|unglazed pottery|, 生地[せいち]:birthplace, 分厚い[ぶあつい, ブあつい]:bulky/massive/thick, 見た目[みため]:appearance, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
如何(いかん)せんジャージの生地が分厚いので
見た目ではわからないかもしれないが
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 嘘[うそ, ウソ]:lie|mistake|unwise move|
この神原駿河 阿良々木先輩に嘘はつかない
but I wouldn't lie to you, Araragi!
I'm wearing this hoodie over bare skin.
上半身[じょうはんしん]:upper half of body/bust, 限る[かぎる]:to restrict/to limit|to be restricted to, 素肌[すはだ]:bare (naked) body/complexion (e.g. face), ジャージ:jersey
上半身に限って言うなら
今の私は素肌にジャージだ
And what about the lower half?
下半身[かはんしん, しもはんしん]:lower half of body
下半身どうなってんだよ
不安[ふあん]:anxiety/uneasiness/insecurity
不安だよ
I'm worried.
Huh?
But, I mean... Calling me out to this place,
at this hour, can only mean one thing, right?
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine)
でもでも こんな時間に こんな場所に
私を呼び出したっていうのは そういうことだろう?
One thing?
そういうこと?
What thing?
どういう:somehow/how/in what way
どういうことだよ
I thought you had finally decided to take my virginity.
ついに:finally/at last|in the end, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 純潔[じゅんけつ]:purity/chastity, 貰う[もらう]:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, 気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy
ついに阿良々木先輩が
私の純潔を貰(もら)ってくれる気になった ということだろう?
Of course not!
だろわねえよ!
Tonight, 9:00 O'clock
Alone, Second Floor
Come To The Classroom
There's something
I want to ask you
Tonight, 9:00 O'clock
Alone, Second Floor
Come To The Classroom
There's something
I want to ask you
Look, Araragi.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
しかし それでも阿良々木先輩
Asking a girl—a woman—to come alone, at night,
to a place away from prying eyes using a suggestive text
女の子[おんなのこ, おんなのコ]:girl/daughter|young woman, 女の子[めのこ]:woman/girl, 女子[じょし, おなご]:woman/girl, 女子[めこ, メコ]:vagina|girl, 夜[よる, よ]:evening/night, 夜[や]:counter for nights, 単身[たんしん]:alone/unaided/away from home, 人気[にんき]:popularity/public favor|condition (e.g. market), 人気[ひとけ]:sign of life/human presence|humanity, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 意味深[いみしん, いみぶか]:with profound (often hidden) meaning/being suggestive/pregnant with significance, メール:email, 呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine), 時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion
女の子を つまり女子を 夜に 単身 人気(ひとけ)のない場所に
意味深なメールで呼び出したという時点で
No Entry
Private Property
Beware
Danger
cannot be taken many different ways.
風[ふり]:swing|appearance|pretence (pretense)||, 風[かぜ]:wind|manner|cold, 受け取る[うけとる]:to receive/to get|to take, 仕方[しかた]:way/method/means
そういう風に受け取られても
それは仕方のないことではないのか?
Alone, Second
Come To
Besides, Araragi.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
それに阿良々木先輩
I accidentally went to the third floor out of excitement when I got here,
さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 勢い[いきおい]:force|influence|impetus|, 余る[あまる]:to remain/to be left over/to be in excess, 二[に, ふた]:two, 二[アル]:two, 階[かい]:storey|stairs|stage (in chronostratigraphy)|, 階[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, 三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 教室[きょうしつ]:classroom|department|single-room school, しまう:to finish/to stop|to close (a business, etc.)
さっき私は 勢い余って
二階ではなく三階の教室に行ってしまったのだが
and there was a bed on one of the tables.
机[つくえ, つき]:desk, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, ベッド:bed, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
机で作られたベッドが用意されていたぞ?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 用意[ようい]:preparation/arrangements/provision
あれは阿良々木先輩が用意したものではないのか?
Didn't you put it there?
心当たり[こころあたり]:having in mind/happening to know of/idea
え? それは本当に心当たりがないんだが...
What? No, I really have no idea.
A bed?
ベッド:bed
ベッド?
You always play dumb.
またまた:again (and again)/once again|You're kidding!, とぼける:to play dumb/to feign ignorance|to play the fool
またまたとぼけちゃって
またまた:again (and again)/once again|You're kidding!
またまたって言われても
Always, huh? I'm not really that type of character.
とぼける:to play dumb/to feign ignorance|to play the fool, 系[けい]:system|corollary|system (range of strata that correspond to a particular time period)|, キャラ:(fictional) character
別に僕 とぼける系のキャラじゃないんだけど
We can call it a fait accompli marriage,
and you could enjoy my virginity right here and now.
既成[きせい]:established/completed/existing, 事実婚[じじつこん]:de facto marriage/common-law marriage, 際[きわ, ぎわ]:edge/brink|time, 際[さい]:on the occasion of/circumstances/juncture, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 純潔[じゅんけつ]:purity/chastity, 貰う[もらう]:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
既成事実婚ということで もうこの際
阿良々木先輩は私の純潔を貰っちゃっていいんじゃないだろうか
だからだろわねえよ
I told you I won't.
What's a fait accompli marriage, anyway?
If anything, it's fait inaccompli
Back to the subject!
So, about why I asked you to come here.
えっと:let me see/well/errr ..., 呼び出す[よびだす]:to summon/to call (e.g. phone)|to invoke (e.g. subroutine), 用件[ようけん]:business/thing to be done/something that should be performed
えっと... それで
お前を呼び出した用件なのだが
Tonight, 9:00 O'clock
Alone, Second Floor
Come To The Classroom
There's something
I want to ask you
Tonight, 9:00 O'clock
Alone, Second Floor
Come To The Classroom
There's something
I want to ask you
訊く[きく]:to hear|to listen (e.g. to music)|to ask||, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
ふむ 何か訊(き)きたいことがあるとのことだったな?
You wanted to ask me something, if I remember correctly.
ああ そうだ
Yeah.
てっきり:surely/certainly/beyond doubt, 訊く[きく]:to hear|to listen (e.g. to music)|to ask||, 純潔[じゅんけつ]:purity/chastity, 対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||, 質問[しつもん]:question/inquiry/enquiry
てっきりその訊きたいことというのが
私の純潔に対する質問なのだと思っていたが
I was thoroughly convinced that your questions
concerned my virginity, but I guess I jumped the gun.
早とちり[はやとちり]:jumping to a wrong conclusion, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
それはどうやら早とちりだったらしい
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 遅い[おそい]:slow|late (e.g. "late at night")|too late|, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||, 通し[とおし]:direct|appetizer|performance of an entire play, 通し[どおし]:throughout.../all through...
早い遅いの問題じゃなく
とちり通しだよお前は
You did, and I hope you won't be
jumping any guns for a while longer.
質問をする[しつもんをする]:to ask a question/to ask questions, 機会[きかい]:chance/opportunity
僕がお前にそんな質問をする機会は
いつまでも来ない
I'd never ask you about that.
訊く[きく]:to hear|to listen (e.g. to music)|to ask||
訊きたいことっていうのは... つまり
What I want to ask you about is...
協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
お前に協力して欲しいことがあるんだけれど
Well, I want you to help me with something.
手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to
手伝ってくれるかってことなんだ
I want to ask you whether you'll help me.
本音を言う[ほんねをいう]:to speak one's mind/to be frank/to tell the truth, 件[くだん]:the aforementioned/the said|the usual, 件[けん]:matter/case/item, 断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
本音を言うと この件
僕はお前には断って欲しいと思っているんだが
To be honest, I'd rather you refused me.
Of course I accept!
断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave
断るわけがないな!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 要請[ようせい]:appeal/call for something|axiom, 応える[こたえる]:to respond/to answer|to affect
この神原駿河が 阿良々木先輩からの要請に応えないなど
あるはずがない!
How could I, Kanbaru Suruga,
ever refuse your requests, Araragi?
たとえ:example|simile/metaphor, たとえ:even if/no matter (what)/if, 天地[てんち, あめつち]:heaven and earth|top and bottom|gods of heaven and earth, 引っ繰り返る[ひっくりかえる]:to be overturned/to be upset/to topple over, ことがある:(something) has occurred/to have done (something)|(something) happens on occasions
たとえ天地が引っ繰り返ることがあろうともだ!
Pigs would sooner fly through a frozen hell!
You see, it's not really my own request.
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, 要請[ようせい]:appeal/call for something|axiom
まあ 必ずしも僕の要請ってわけじゃないんだが
I'm just the intermediary.
あくまで:to the end/to the bitter end|after all, 仲介[ちゅうかい]:agency/intermediation
僕はあくまで仲介であって
しかも:moreover/furthermore|nevertheless, 協力[きょうりょく]:cooperation/collaboration, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to, 内容[ないよう]:subject/contents/matter, 詳しい[くわしい]:detailed/full|knowing very well
しかも 協力して欲しいことの内容も
詳しくは知らないって言うか
Besides, I don't really know myself what you'd be helping with.
You don't know?
知らない?
No, not at all.
うん 何にも知らない
I was probably never told on purpose.
So if you refused me here, that would be the end of it.
断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., おしまい:the end/closing|That's it
だから お前がここで断ってくれたら
それでこの話がおしまいになるから
そっちのほうがいい
I would prefer that.
Of course, should you decide to help, I would do my utmost to protect your body from injury.
もちろん:of course/certainly/naturally, あくまで:to the end/to the bitter end|after all, 手伝う[てつだう]:to help/to assist|to contribute to, 身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 及ぶ[およぶ]:to reach|to be up to the task|to compare with||, 全力を尽くす[ぜんりょくをつくす]:to do one's best/to put forth every effort
もちろん お前があくまで手伝ってくれるっていうのであれば
お前の身に危険が及ばないよう 僕は全力を尽くすつもりだけれど
ははは:ha ha ha (laughter), 身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 気にする[きにする]:to mind (negative nuance)/to care about/to worry, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
ははは 私の身など
阿良々木先輩が気にする必要はないのだ
You don't have to worry about my body.
気になる[きになる]:to be on one's mind|to feel like|to fancy, 身[み]:body|oneself|one's place|, 身[むくろ]:(dead) body/corpse, 体積[たいせき]:capacity/volume, ほんの:mere/only/just, 一部[いちぶ]:one part/one portion|one copy (e.g. of a document)
それでもどうしても気になると言うのであれば
身の体積のほんの一部
If you want to ponder my body,
then you're welcome to ponder the volume of my breasts.
即ち[すなわち]:that is/namely/i.e., おっぱい:breasts/boobies|breast milk, 辺り[あたり, ほとり]:on the bank of|(in the) neighbourhood|around (Sunday, last year, etc...)|, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||
即(すなわ)ち
おっぱいの辺りのことだけを考えてくれていればよい
The hell I will!
よいわけあるか
That I have come running to this cram school against all odds should be enough answer for you, Araragi.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 訊く[きく]:to hear|to listen (e.g. to music)|to ask||, 万難[ばんなん]:many obstacles/innumerable difficulties, 排する[はいする]:to push aside|to align|to push open, 学習塾[がくしゅうじゅく]:private night-school/tutoring school (math, English, etc.), 駆けつける[かけつける]:to run to/to come running/to rush (someplace), 既に[すでに, すんでに]:already/too late, 答[こたえ, いらえ]:answer/reply/response
もしも阿良々木先輩の訊きたいことがそれならば
私が万難を排してこの学習塾に駆けつけたことが 既に答だとは思わないか?
うん まあ... そうだな
Uh, I guess.
I was overwhelmed by the desire to serve your every need.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 奉仕[ほうし]:service/ministry|offering goods at a reduced price, しょう:workman/artisan|craft, しょう:quotient|dealing/dealer
阿良々木先輩にご奉仕(ほうし)したくてしたくて
しょうがない私なのだ
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||
今夜は読みたかった本があったというのに
There was a book I wanted to read this evening,
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally
阿良々木先輩のためにわざわざ来てやったのだぞ?
but I came here just for you.
A book you wanted to read?
読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||
読みたかった本って
I'm competing with a book now?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 優先順位[ゆうせんじゅんい]:priority/order of precedence, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 競う[きそう]:to compete with|to emulate
先輩の優先順位が本と競ってるじゃないか
So, Kanbaru.
じゃあ神原
今夜[こんや]:this evening/tonight, いったい:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")/...in the world (e.g. "why in the world?")|one object, いったい:region/zone/whole place, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
今夜はいったい何を読むつもりだったんだ?
What did you want to read tonight?
Something by Yamamoto Shuugorou of course!
山本[やまもと]:foot of a mountain|mine|owner of a mountain, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, 決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
山本(やまもと)周五郎(しゅうごろう)先生に決まっておろう
Which one by him?
ちなみ:association/link|pledge (esp. for marriage), 山本[やまもと]:foot of a mountain|mine|owner of a mountain, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
ちなみに山本周五郎の何を読んでるんだよ
読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||
お前が読んでる本なら僕も読みたい
If you like it, I want to read it too.
お勧め[おすすめ, オススメ]:recommendation/advice/suggestion, 小説[しょうせつ]:novel/(short) story, たくさん:a lot/lots|enough
だったらお勧めのＢＬ小説もたくさんあるのだが
Oh, if that's the case, I have some boy love novels to recommend!
山本[やまもと]:foot of a mountain|mine|owner of a mountain, からにする:to empty/to vacate/to evacuate
まずは山本周五郎からにしてくれ
Let's start with Yamamoto Shuugorou.
そうか じゃあ
Okay. Let's see.
美少女[びしょうじょ]:beautiful girl, 一番乗り[いちばんのり]:leader of a charge/first to arrive
"美少女一番乗り"と言うのだが
It's called "First at the Maiden."
Liar!
嘘をつく[うそをつく, ウソをつく]:to tell a lie/to fib
嘘をつけ!
As if the renowned Yamamoto Shuugorou would choose a title like that!
山本[やまもと]:foot of a mountain|mine|owner of a mountain, 先生[せんせい, せんじょう]:teacher|with names of teachers, etc. as an honorific|previous existence, 先生[シーサン]:boy, タイトル:title, 本[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 本[ほん]:book|this|main||, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
山本周五郎先生がそんなタイトルの本を書くか!
実際[じっさい]:practicality|reality|bhutakoti (limit of reality), 仕方ない[しかたない]:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
いや でも実際に出ているんだから仕方ないだろう
But it really exists... What are you going to do?
現状[げんじょう]:present condition/existing state/status quo, 品切れ[しなぎれ]:out of stock/sold out, 重版[じゅうはん]:second edition/additional printing, 未定[みてい]:not yet fixed/undecided/pending, 状態[じょうたい]:current status/condition/situation, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
まあ現状 品切れ重版未定状態ではあるが
I guess it's actually out of print with no second edition in sight, though.
Back to the subject!
All right, Kanbaru.
さて 神原
頼みごと[たのみごと]:favour/favor
頼みごとなんだが
What I was going to ask you...
I'm sorry to spring this on you, but would you come with me?
早速[さっそく]:at once/immediately/without delay, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
じゃあ 早速で悪いんだが
ちょっと一緒に来てくれるか
ん? なんだ
Huh?
用事[ようじ]:tasks/things to do/errand
ここに用事があるわけじゃないのか?
I thought everything was going to go down here.
単なる[たんなる]:mere/simple/sheer, 待ち合わせる[まちあわせる]:to rendezvous/to meet at a prearranged place and time/to arrange to meet, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
ああ ここは単なるお前との待ち合わせ場所だよ
No, I only meant to meet you here.
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 待ち合わせる[まちあわせる]:to rendezvous/to meet at a prearranged place and time/to arrange to meet
へえ... だったら別に
家で待ち合わせてもよかっただろうに
So... Why didn't we meet at home, then?
Huh? Why did I make this our meeting point, anyway?
学習塾[がくしゅうじゅく]:private night-school/tutoring school (math, English, etc.), 跡[あと]:trace|site|scar, 跡[せき]:trace, 待ち合わせる[まちあわせる]:to rendezvous/to meet at a prearranged place and time/to arrange to meet, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho, 指定[してい]:designation/specification/assignment
あれ なんで僕は
この学習塾跡を待ち合わせ場所に指定したんだっけ?
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken
確か...
I think...
構う[かまう]:to mind|to care for|to prepare for||
まあ 構わん
Well, I don't mind.
仔細[しさい]:reasons/circumstances|hindrance, 問う[とう]:to ask|to charge (e.g. with a crime)|without regard to|
仔細(しさい)は問わない
I won't pry.
どこにでも行こう
Let's go wherever you want.
大丈夫
I'll be fine.
遺書[いしょ]:note left by dead person/suicide note|posthumous work, 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
遺書はもう書いてきた
I wrote my will.
怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
怖いことすんな!
That's depressing!
身構える[みがまえる]:to put oneself on guard/to stand ready/to square off
まあ 今からそんな身構えなくとも 神原
You don't have to get so worked up, Kanbaru.
待ち合わせる[まちあわせる]:to rendezvous/to meet at a prearranged place and time/to arrange to meet, 場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
これから行くのもまた ただの待ち合わせ場所だよ
We're just heading to a different meeting point now.
A rendezvous point...
合流[ごうりゅう]:confluence (of rivers)/merge (of traffic)|union (e.g. of forces), 地点[ちてん]:site/point on a map/spot
合流地点って言うのか...
Basically, I want to introduce you to someone.
お前に会わせたい人がいるんだ
Oh my, look at you.
やおや:greengrocer, まったく:really/truly|indeed, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
おやおや まったく困った人だ
Whom did you try to impress and how?
対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||, どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 見栄を張る[みえをはる]:to be pretentious/to put on airs
誰に対してどんな見栄を張ったんだ?
With grades? Contacts? Popularity?
成績[せいせき]:results/record/grades, 人間関係[にんげんかんけい]:human relations, 度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol)
成績か人間関係か? モテ度か?
No. I don't want you to back up my story.
違う
合わせる[あわせる]:to match (rhythm, speed, etc.)|to join together|to face||, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
合わせたい話があるんじゃない
会わせたい人がいるんだ
I just want you to meet someone.
紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
お前を紹介して欲しいって言われてて
They said they wanted to meet you.
ふうん:misfortune/bad luck/ill luck, ふうん:hmm/well ...|roughly
ふうん まあいいや
All righty.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman)
阿良々木先輩の言うことなら
まず間違いあるまい
I'm sure what you say is all fine.
I feel like you'd be better off trusting me about half as much as you do.
対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||, 信頼度[しんらいど]:dependability/credibility/coefficient of confidence, 半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 減らす[へらす]:to abate/to decrease/to diminish, 欲しい[ほしい]:wanted/wished for|I want (you) to
できれば僕に対する信頼度を半分くらいに減らして欲しいのだが
But don't worry.
でも 大丈夫だ
少ない[すくない]:few/a little/scarce, 男子[だんし]:youth/young man, 女子[じょし, おなご]:woman/girl, 女子[めこ, メコ]:vagina|girl, 告白[こくはく]:confession|profession of love|confession of sins (e.g. the confessional), 紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral, 仲介[ちゅうかい]:agency/intermediation
少なくとも男子や女子が お前に告白するとか
そういう紹介とか仲介とかじゃないから
What I know for sure is that some boy or girl
won't confess their love for you this evening.
紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral, 構う[かまう]:to mind|to care for|to prepare for||
別にそういう紹介でも構わないぞ?
I wouldn't mind that, anyway.
普通[ふつう]:general|normally|local train, 断る[ことわる]:to refuse|to inform|to ask leave
普通に断るし
I'd just turn them down.
If you go and say, "Alas, it was me!"
then of course things are different.
紹介[しょうかい]:introduction/presentation/referral, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, 落ち[おち, オチ]:slip|outcome|punch line (of a joke), 無論[むろん]:of course/naturally, 話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc.
"紹介したい人は...僕でした!"みたいな落ちならば
無論 話は別だが
隙[すき, げき]:gap|break|chink (in one's armor, armour)|, 付き合う[つきあう]:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with
隙を見ては僕と付き合おうとするな
Don't try to seize every opportunity to go out with me.
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 肉食系[にくしょくけい]:man's man/man aggressively pursuing sex and riches/carnivore
どんな肉食系だよ
How can you be so hell-bent on carnal relations?
付き合う[つきあう]:to associate with/to keep company with|to go along with, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother
いや 付き合おうとはしていない
But I don't want to go out with you.
肉体[にくたい]:the body/the flesh, 関係[かんけい]:relation|participation|influence||
肉体関係だけでいい
Just the carnal part is enough.
肉食系[にくしょくけい]:man's man/man aggressively pursuing sex and riches/carnivore, 一方的[いっぽうてき]:one-sided/unilateral/arbitrary, 捕食[ほしょく]:predation/eating prey/preying upon
肉食系だけに 一方的に捕食したい
A carnal carnivore needs their catch.
I'm getting goose bumps.
ぞっと:shuddering/shivering/trembling
ぞっとするぜ
I don't believe in emotional attachment!
精神的[せいしんてき]:mental/emotional, 繋がり[つながり]:connection/link/relationship, 信ずる[しんずる]:to believe/to believe in/to place trust in
私は精神的な繋(つな)がりなど信じない
人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death), 一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||
お前の人生に一体なにがあった
What on Earth happened in your life?
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, 考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||
つーか お前一体何を考えて生きてるんだよ
And by what do you live it?
If it looks to you like I think about life, you should see an optometrist.
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife), 病院[びょういん]:hospital
私が何かを考えているように見えるんだったら
病院に行ったほうがよいな
閑話休題[かんわきゅうだい]:Now let's return to the main subject/To return from the digression,.. (in a conversation, speech, or story-telling)
閑話休題
Back to the subject!
Okey-dokey, Araragi.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
オーキードーキー 阿良々木先輩
委細[いさい]:details/particulars, 承知[しょうち]:knowledge|consent|forgiving
委細承知
I have grasped the details.
参る[まいる]:to go|to be defeated|to be annoyed||
では参ろうではないか
Let us venture forth.
場所[ばしょ]:place|room|basho
どこだかわからない場所に
誰だかわからない人に会いに!
Let us go to meet someone I don't know somewhere I don't know!
You can be pretty amazing.
やっぱ:too/also|still, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
やっぱすげえな お前...
Deleaveture!
でっぱつだ!
Huh? Who's that? Another visitor?
来客[らいきゃく, らいかく]:visitor/caller
ん? なんだ 来客か?
這入る[はいる]:to enter|to break into|to join||
這入っていいぞ
Come in!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 知り合い[しりあい]:acquaintance
え? 阿良々木先輩の知り合いが来たんじゃないのか?
Isn't that some acquaintance of yours?
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
私の他にも誰かを呼んでいたということではないのか?
I thought you had called someone else here beside me.
呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
いや 僕が呼んだのはお前だけで
No, I only called you...
か 神原っ
K-Kanbaru—
Take cover, Araragi!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 伏せる[ふせる]:to lie down/to retire/to go to bed (with an illness), 伏せる[ふせる]:to lay something upside down/to turn something over|to cover
阿良々木先輩 伏せてろ!
Empty
Araragi, this isn't just empty... It's an empty shell.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 空[から]:emptiness/vacuum/blank, 空[そら]:sky|weather|far-off place||, 殻[から]:shell/husk/hull, 殻[がら]:chicken bones (e.g. for soup)|poor-quality coke (coal)|left-overs
阿良々木先輩 空と言うより
殻(から)だったぞ
Shell
There was no resistance at all.
手ごたえ[てごたえ]:response (felt in the hands)/resistance|reaction, 過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much)
手ごたえがなさ過ぎだ
空振り[からぶり]:striking (at something) and missing/in vain, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
空振りしたかと思ったくらいだ
I felt like I hit the empty air.
なんなのだ あれは?
What is that?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
阿良々木先輩の友達か?
A friend of yours?
鎧[よろい]:armor/armour, 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
僕に鎧の友達はいねえよ
None of my friends is a suit of armor.
どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 友達[ともだち]:friend/companion
ではどんな友達がいるのだろう
Then what sort of friends do you have?
あれ...
Huh?
Well, well...
どうした神原
What's wrong, Kanbaru?
一式[いっしき]:complete set/all/everything, 揃う[そろう]:to become complete|to be equal|to gather, 甲冑[かっちゅう]:armor and helmet (armour), 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
いや 一式揃った甲冑だと思っていたのだが
よく見たら 足りないな
Oh, I just... thought it was a full suit of armor,
but now that I look at it carefully, it's missing something.
足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
足りない?
Missing?
Yeah. You see, we have five or six suits of armor at home too,
家[いえ]:house|family|lineage, 家[うち, ち]:house/home (one's own)|(one's) family, 甲冑[かっちゅう]:armor and helmet (armour), 五[ご, いつ]:five, 五[ウー]:five, 六[ろく, む]:six, 六[リュー]:six, 個[こ, コ]:counter for articles|counter for military units|individual, 個[か, カ]:counter for the ichi-ni-san counting system (usu. directly preceding the item being counted)/a noun read using its on-yomi
うん ほら 私の家にも甲冑は五
六個あるんだけれど
比べる[くらべる]:to compare/to make a comparison|to compete, 鎧[よろい]:armor/armour, 武者[むしゃ]:warrior, 肝心[かんじん]:essential/fundamental/crucial
それと比べてみると あの鎧武者には
肝心のものがない
and compared to them, I feel like this one is missing something vital.
To me it didn't seem like something was missing.
限り[かぎり]:limit|degree|as far as possible||, 限り[きり]:end|bounds|delivery date (of a futures contract)||, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient, 部品[ぶひん]:parts/accessories/components, なんか:things like .../or something like that ... (often derogatory), なんか:something
でも 僕が見る限り
足りない部品なんかなかったように思うけれど
ああそうだ 神原
Oh, Kanbaru.
甲冑[かっちゅう]:armor and helmet (armour), 造詣[ぞうけい]:deep knowledge/attainments/scholarship, 一回[いっかい]:once/one time/one round, 組み直す[くみなおす]:to reschedule/to recompose/to recross (one's legs)
甲冑への造詣(ぞうけい)があるって言うんだったら
あれをもう一回 組み直してみてくれるか?
Since you have such intimate knowledge of armor sets, could you assemble it again?
What, me?
え? 私がか?
Well, I don't know how to assemble it.
甲冑[かっちゅう]:armor and helmet (armour), 組み立て[くみたて]:construction/framework/erection
だって僕には甲冑の組み立てかたと
かわからないもん
指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 組み立てる[くみたてる]:to assemble/to set up/to construct
じゃあ私が指示するから
阿良々木先輩が組み立てたらどうだろう
How about I tell you what to do and you do it?
You know no hesitation when it comes to using your senior, huh?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 躊躇[ちゅうちょ]:hesitation/indecision/vacillation
先輩を使うことに躊躇(ちゅうちょ)がないよな お前は
まあいいけど
Well, all right.
I will demonstrate to you that I can do more than lie on the floor and shield my head!
うつ伏せ[うつぶせ]:lying on one's face/upside-down, 見せる[みせる]:to show/to display
僕がただ 言われるがままに
うつ伏せになっているだけの男ではないところを見せてやろう
うつ伏せ[うつぶせ]:lying on one's face/upside-down, 仰向け[あおむけ]:face up
うつ伏せだけじゃなく
仰向(あおむ)けにもなれるところを
I can also look up!
I don't really want the person I respect to look up at me.
尊敬[そんけい]:respect/esteem/reverence, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 仰向け[あおむけ]:face up
尊敬する先輩が仰向けになっているところこそ
見たくないが
組み立てる[くみたてる]:to assemble/to set up/to construct, 直す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
でも なぜ組み立て直す必要があるのだ?
But why do you want to have it assembled anyway?
Look, maybe it moves again if we reassemble it.
組み立てる[くみたてる]:to assemble/to set up/to construct, ひょっと:possibly/perhaps|unintentionally, 動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
いや 組み立てたら
ひょっとしたらまた動き出すかもしれないじゃないか
What this armor lacks
甲冑[かっちゅう]:armor and helmet (armour), 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient
この甲冑に足りないもの
is...
それは
Stand back, Araragi!
下がる[さがる]:to come down|to hang|to move back||, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
下がっていろ 阿良々木先輩!
Fist
Punch
Touch
Body
Hit
Abdomen
Push
Left
Strike
Hand
Patch
Power
Energy Drain
Touch
Left
Monkey
Rain
Pain
Punch
Jaw
Fist
Energy Drain
Hit
Touch
Monkey
Neck
Fly
Throat
Hit
Pain
Kanbaru!
神原!?
Stay there!
く 来るな!
え...?
いや なんかこいつ
Isn't he
getting tougher?
だんだん:gradually/by degrees|steps, だんだん:thank you (dialect from the Izumo region of Shimane Prefecture), 頑丈[がんじょう]:solid/firm/stout
だんだん頑丈になってないか
あ—
A—
Araragi...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
阿良々木先輩
Run away.
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away
逃げろ
That was the one order I could not obey.
だんだん:gradually/by degrees|steps, だんだん:thank you (dialect from the Izumo region of Shimane Prefecture), 頑丈[がんじょう]:solid/firm/stout, 鎧[よろい]:armor/armour, 武者[むしゃ]:warrior
だんだん頑丈(がんじょう)になる鎧武者
The armor became gradually tougher.
対照的[たいしょうてき]:contrastive, だんだん:gradually/by degrees|steps, だんだん:thank you (dialect from the Izumo region of Shimane Prefecture), 弱る[よわる]:to weaken/to be troubled/to be downcast, 気付く[きづく]:to notice/to recognize/to recognise
対照的に 神原がだんだん弱っていることに
僕は気付いていなかった
And, conversely, I hadn't realized
Kanbaru became gradually weaker.
Her first punch struck his torso.
最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 胴体[どうたい]:body/trunk/torso, 一撃[いちげき]:blow/hit/poke, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
最初に胴体に一撃を入れ
Another punch struck his chin,
一撃[いちげき]:blow/hit/poke, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||, 顎[あご, がく]:chin/jaw, 顎[あぎと]:chin/jaw|gills, 殴る[なぐる]:to strike/to hit/to beat
また一撃を入れ 顎を殴ったところで
and she went down to one knee afterwards.
片膝をつく[かたひざをつく]:to kneel down on one knee/to genuflect
彼女は片膝をついた
時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion, くずおれる:to collapse (physically or emotionally)/to fall down, 不思議[ふしぎ]:wonder/miracle/strange
あの時点で
どうして神原がくずおれたのか不思議だったが
I thought it strange that she lost strength there,
but I only understood once I saw her drop to the ground right after her tackle.
タックル:tackle (e.g. rugby), しがみつく:to cling, 直後[ちょくご]:immediately following, 倒れる[たおれる]:to fall|to be forced to bed (by illness, etc.)|to die||, 得心[とくしん]:consenting to/being convinced of/being satisfied
タックルでしがみついた直後に倒れた彼女を見て
僕は得心(とくしん)した
エナジー:energy, ドレイン:drain
エナジードレイン
Energy drain.
Energy Drain
なんで?
Why?
古風[こふう]:old-fashioned/archaic/antique, 時代錯誤[じだいさくご]:anachronism, 鎧[よろい]:armor/armour, 武者[むしゃ]:warrior, 吸血鬼[きゅうけつき]:vampire/bloodsucker, さながら:just like, エナジー:energy, ドレイン:drain
どうして古風な 時代錯誤な鎧武者が
吸血鬼さながらのエナジードレインを使ってくる
Why does this old, anachronistic armor use the energy drain of vampires?
What is that?
なんなんだ あいつは?
What's wrong with you?
な なんなんだ お前
Why are you here?
なんのつもりだ
What do you have against us?
達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 恨み[うらみ]:resentment/grudge|matter for regret
僕達に何の恨みがある
Why are you doing this?
どうしてこんなことをするんだ
Stay away.
If you can move, run away now.
Run Away
I Won't
I'll come from behind
and hit his knees,
so use that chance
to run away.
Even your eye contact is silly.
アイコンタクト:eye contact, 馬鹿[ばか, バカ]:fool|trivial matter|foolish|
なんでアイコンタクトでも馬鹿なんだ
Hanekawa...
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
羽川先輩
退く[どく, のく]:to step aside/to move (i.e. out of the way)|to resign, 退く[しりぞく, しぞく]:to step back|to withdraw (from the presence of a superior)|to resign|
ここらが退きどきかのう!
Perhaps I should take my leave here.
It appears I have been met with serious interference.
生半[なまなか]:halfway-done/mediocre|half-heartedly, 邪魔[じゃま]:hindrance|to visit (somebody's home)|demon who hinders Buddhist training
どうやら生半(なまなか)ならぬ邪魔が入ったようじゃ
Did I step on the tiger's tail?
虎の尾[とらのお]:tiger's tail|gooseneck loosestrife (species of flowering plant, Lysimachia clethroides)|Asplenium incisum (species of spleenwort), 踏む[ふむ]:to step on|to experience|to estimate||
虎の尾でも踏んだかのう?
拙者[せっしゃ]:I (primarily used by samurai)/me, とても:very/awfully|(not) at all, 対処[たいしょ]:dealing with/coping with, きれる:to break/to snap|to be injured, きれる:to be able to wear/to fit into
今の拙者ではこれにはとても対処しきれぬわ!
I stand no chance as I am now.
時機[じき]:opportunity/chance/time, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
どうやら時機が悪かったと見える
I see this was not my chance after all.
My master is not here either.
我が[わが]:my/our/one's own, あるじ:head (of a household)/proprietor (of a store)|entertaining someone as one's guest
我があるじもおらぬようじゃし
I shall return!
出直す[でなおす]:to make a fresh start/to turn over a new leaf|to call again
ここは出直しじゃ!
You will go home now without detours.
おぬし:you (when referring to one's equals or inferiors), 寄り道[よりみち]:dropping in on the way/breaking one's journey/making a stopover, まっすぐ:straight (ahead)/direct|straightforward, おうち:hollow/low ground/basin, おうち:interior/backwoods/hinterland, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
おぬしも寄り道せず
まっすぐおうちに帰るがよかろう!
鎧[よろい]:armor/armour, 武者[むしゃ]:warrior, 首[くび, クビ]:neck|head|dismissal, 首[しゅきゅう, しるし]:decapitated head of an enemy, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain, ことによる:depending on the circumstances|due to (with modifying verb), 声[こえ]:voice, 吸い取る[すいとる]:to suck up/to absorb/to squeeze (money)
あの鎧武者は 僕の首を強くつかむことによって
僕の声を吸い取ったのだ
When the armor wrangled my head, it took my voice.
エナジー:energy, ドレイン:drain
エナジードレイン
Energy drain.
タックル:tackle (e.g. rugby), 再現[さいげん]:reappearance/reproduction/return
神原のタックルを再現したように
Just as it recreated Kanbaru's tackle,
it recreated my voice.
声[こえ]:voice, 再現[さいげん]:reappearance/reproduction/return
今は僕の声を 再現した
合流[ごうりゅう]:confluence (of rivers)/merge (of traffic)|union (e.g. of forces), 伝える[つたえる]:to convey/to report/to transmit
キスショットと合流したら 伝えておけい!
If you see Kiss-Shot, tell her...
少し[すこし]:small quantity|little while|short distance, 回復[かいふく]:restoration/rehabilitation|recovery (from an illness), 拙者[せっしゃ]:I (primarily used by samurai)/me, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 妖刀[ようとう]:bewitched sword/magical sword/demon sword, 返す[かえす]:to return (something)|to turn over|to pay back|, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
もう少し回復したら 拙者の大事な妖刀
"心渡(こころわたり)" 返してもらいにいくと!
that I will collect my treasured demon sword, Heart Span, once I have recovered.
やはり:too/also|still, 刀[かたな, とう]:(single-edged) sword|dagger|scalpel, 足りる[たりる]:to be sufficient|to be worth doing|to be sufficient, 鎧[よろい]:armor/armour, 武者[むしゃ]:warrior, 締まる[しまる]:to be shut|to be firm (of a body, face, etc.)|to be locked||
やはり刀が足りなければ
鎧武者は締まらぬわ!
What is a samurai without his sword?
It has been four hundred years since I lent it to her.
なにせ:at any rate/anyhow, 貸す[かす]:to lend/to loan|to rent out, ござる:to be
なにせ貸してから四百年でござる
延滞料[えんたいりょう]:arrears/late fee/delinquent account charge, 覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
延滞料は覚悟しておくがよかろうとな!
Tell her to prepare for a late fee!
What was that warrior, Araragi?
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 鎧[よろい]:armor/armour, 武者[むしゃ]:warrior
阿良々木先輩 なんだったんだ?
あの鎧武者は
甲冑[かっちゅう]:armor and helmet (armour), 佩刀[はいとう]:carrying a sword, してい:servant/janitor/messenger, してい:older sister and younger brother, おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
甲冑が佩刀(はいとう)していないのは
おかしいと思っていたが
I thought it was strange that no sword accompanied the armor, but...
He mentioned the demon sword, Heart Span, and Kiss-Shot...
妖刀[ようとう]:bewitched sword/magical sword/demon sword, 確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken
しかし妖刀"心渡"って 確か
それに キスショットって
Let's worry about that later.
後回し[あとまわし]:putting off/postponing
今は 後回しだ それは
Hey, Kanbaru...
神原
Can you jump up to the ceiling from here?
助走[じょそう]:approach run (long jump), ツーステップ:two-step, くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 天井[てんじょう]:ceiling/ceiling price, 手が届く[てがとどく]:to be able to reach/to be within one's reach|to be near (a certain age)
お前なら 助走なしでも ワン...ツーステップくらい で
なんとか天井まで 手が届くんじゃないのか?
よじのぼれる:to climb/to clamber (over, up)/to scramble (up)
よじのぼれるんじゃないのか?
Then climb up?
三[さん, み]:three|tri-, 三[サン]:three, 階[かい]:storey|stairs|stage (in chronostratigraphy)|, 階[しな]:article|quality|flirtatiousness, エレベーター:elevator/lift, シャフト:shaft, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||
で 三階から
エレベーターシャフトを通って一階に
Then you can take the elevator shaft down to the first floor—
いくら:how much?/how many?|even, 後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student, 買い被る[かいかぶる]:to overestimate/to make too much of, 過ぎ[すぎ]:past/after|too (much), 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
それはいくらなんでも
後輩を買(か)い被(かぶ)り過ぎだ 阿良々木先輩
You overestimate me, Araragi.
脚力[きゃくりょく, きゃくりき]:leg strength/walking ability
私の脚力は そこまでではない
I'm not that athletic.
Not even I can jump to the ceiling carrying a larger boy.
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 年上[としうえ]:older/senior, 男子[だんし]:youth/young man, 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried, 抱える[かかえる]:to hold or carry under or in the arms|to have (esp. problems, debts, etc.)|to employ, 天井[てんじょう]:ceiling/ceiling price, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump, ジャンプ:jump
さすがの私も 年上の男子一人を抱えて
天井まで飛べるほどのジャンプ力はない
そっか
I see.
Araragi.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
阿良々木先輩
どうした神原
Yes, Kanbaru?
Will you sleep with me?
初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
私の初めて もらってくれないか
Don't put yourself into the mood!
覚悟を決める[かくごをきめる]:to prepare oneself (for the worst)/to resolve oneself
覚悟を決めるな!
処女[しょじょ]:virgin/maiden
処女のまま死にたくない
I don't want to die a virgin!
This isn't the time for confessions!
アウト:out
カミングアウトをするな
Because you always
say stuff like that
the story you narrated
was on the backburner.
Oh, well.
まあいい
悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 死に様[しにざま]:manner of death, ではある:to be (in contrast to something that is not the case)
これもまあ 悪い死に様ではあるまい
This isn't such a bad way to die.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 共[ども]:first-person plural (or singular)|second or third person plural (implies speaker is of higher status than those referred to), 共[とも]:together with|same|both|, 死ぬ[しぬ]:to die|to lose spirit|to cease, 望む[のぞむ]:to desire|to wish for|to see
阿良々木先輩と共に死ねるなら
望むところだ
Dying together with you is all I wish for.
Uh, sorry.
いや すまん神原
対する[たいする]:to face (each other)|to be directed toward (the future, etc.)|to receive (a client, etc.)||, 思える[おもえる]:to seem/to appear likely
僕 お前に対してそこまでは思えない
I don't feel the same way about you.
傷つく[きずつく]:to be wounded|to get hurt feelings|to get damaged
え? それは傷つくな
Ouch. That hurts.
共[ども]:first-person plural (or singular)|second or third person plural (implies speaker is of higher status than those referred to), 共[とも]:together with|same|both|, 相手[あいて]:companion|other party|opponent (sports, etc.), 一人[ひとり, いちにん]:one person|alone/unmarried
僕が共に死にたいと思う相手は ただ一人
There is only one person I want to die together with.
一体[いったい]:...the heck (e.g. "what the heck?")|one object|one form||, 金髪[きんぱつ, キンパツ]:blond hair, 怪異[かいい]:strangeness/mystery|ghost
ただ一体の 金髪の怪異だけなのだ
The blonde oddity.
And she isn't here right now.
彼女は今 ここにいない
Therefore we must escape this blazing building.
炎[ほのお, ほむら]:flame/blaze|flames (of intense emotion, e.g. love, jealousy, anger), 炎[えん]:-itis (indicating an inflammatory disease), ビルディング:building, 達[たち]:pluralizing suffix (esp. for people & animals; formerly honorific), 達[だち, ダチ]:friend, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 脱出[だっしゅつ]:escape/break-out|prolapse
だからこそ この炎のビルディングから
僕達は生きて 脱出しなければならない
仕方ない[しかたない]:it can't be helped/it's inevitable/it's no use
仕方ねえ
All right.
覚悟を決める[かくごをきめる]:to prepare oneself (for the worst)/to resolve oneself
覚悟を決めるしかねえか
Guess it's time to man up.
To do to me what only a man can?
初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something, 覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness
ん? 私の初めてをもらう覚悟をか
大それた[だいそれた]:outrageous/monstrous/appalling, 覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness, 決める[きめる]:to decide|to clinch (a victory)|to persist in doing||
そんな大それた覚悟は決められない
I couldn't bring myself to do that.
We can still jump out of a window as a last-ditch effort.
焼け死ぬ[やけしぬ]:to be burnt to death, 一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 八[はち, や]:eight, 八[パー]:eight, 窓[まど]:window, 飛び降りる[とびおりる]:to jump down/to jump off/to jump from
このままここで焼け死ぬよりは
一か八か 窓から飛び降りるしかないだろう
Yeah.
そうだな
I also thought that was our last choice.
私もそれしかないと思っていた
Liar
You were thinking about something
completely different.
Don't get this wrong, Araragi.
The first step is with the right foot.
But since I'm left-handed, I sometimes confuse left and right.
ダイナマイト:dynamite, 消火[しょうか]:fire fighting/extinguishing a fire
ダイナマイト消火って言うんだよね
こういうのは
This is called Dynamite Firefighting, I believe.
死ぬ[しぬ]:to die|to lose spirit|to cease
こんなところで死ねると思うな
Don't think you're dying here.
鬼[おに, き]:oni|spirit of a deceased person|ogre-like person (i.e. fierce, relentless, merciless, etc.)||
鬼(おに)いちゃんを殺すのはこの僕だ
If anything will kill you, it'll be me.
I hear your laughter near me
You were supposed to be there forever
I breathed onto the classroom window and wrote your name
only to panic and wipe it with my sleeve
I heard your voice from the hallway
and went home in hurry to hide my feelings
At some point I became unable
to talk to you normally
I can hear your laughter a ways away
You were supposed to be next to me forever
You knew how I felt
even when I said nothing
Now I know how important you were to me,
but we will never see each other again